<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Roula Nezi</title>
    <link>/</link>
      <atom:link href="/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <description>Roula Nezi</description>
    <generator>Wowchemy (https://wowchemy.com)</generator><language>en-us</language><copyright>© Roula Nezi</copyright>
    <image>
      <url>/images/icon_hua2ec155b4296a9c9791d015323e16eb5_11927_512x512_fill_lanczos_center_2.png</url>
      <title>Roula Nezi</title>
      <link>/</link>
    </image>
    
    <item>
      <title></title>
      <link>/admin/config.yml</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>/admin/config.yml</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title></title>
      <link>/contact/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>/contact/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title></title>
      <link>/data/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>/data/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;The 2011 Political Parties Expert Survey in Greece&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Kostas Gemenis and Roula Nezi, November 2011 - January 2012&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The aim of this study is to estimate the ideological and policy positions of political parties in Greece during the ‘Great Recession’. The survey includes expert estimates regarding parties’ positions on general ideological and specific policy scales (Left-Right, social and moral issues, state intervention in the economy, environment, immigration, European and foreign policy, etc) as well as estimates of party leader positions and internal party dissent on the issue of solving the debt/deficit problem. The data are comparable to previously conducted expert surveys on political parties.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;font size=&#34;-1&#34;&gt;The dataset is archived at the Data Archiving and Networked Services (DANS), Fedora Identifier: easy-dataset:48574.&lt;/font&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;You may download the report here:
&lt;a href=&#34;https://roulanezi.files.wordpress.com/2017/03/expert_survey_report.pdf&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;The 2011 expert survey report&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;br&gt;
&lt;br&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Political attitudes in Greece&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A panel study, conducted in 2015 measuring political attitudes, including electoral turnout and voting preferences. The datasets also include data on attitudes on a wide range of issues, evaluations of the economy and a range of survey experiments on issues related to the economic crisis. The datasets are archived at GESIS-Leibniz Institute for the Social Sciences.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;You may download the dataset &lt;a href=&#34;https://datorium.gesis.org/xmlui/handle/10.7802/1529&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title></title>
      <link>/experiments/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>/experiments/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;SURVEY EXPERIMENTS&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;br&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;em&gt;Acceptance of austerity policies: Evidence from a survey experiment&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;What drives people to accept or resist austerity? This paper examines the way framing provided by populist leaders can activate certain political attitudes towards austerity. Accepting that the key mechanism in populist framing is the ability to attribute blame to other agents, we argue that populism is about the redistribution of anger (Pappas 2014). Therefore our main research question is: Does the framing of austerity policies affect the way those policies are perceived by the general public? We employ a vignette social experiment where stories represent real situations (leaders’ official statements on austerity in Greece) to elicit voters’ preferences and judgments.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Interested to learn more about our research on austerity politics? You may listen, my co-author, Theofanis Exadaktylos,  presenting our research at the University of Birmingham &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.birmingham.ac.uk/schools/government-society/centres/iccs/news/2018/01/p-acceptance-austerity-policies.aspx&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;br&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;em&gt;Economic voting and unemployment: Evidence from a survey experiment&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The state of the economy has been traditionally considered as an important determinant of political behaviour. The theory of economic voting suggests that voters will support the party in government when the economy is good but will vote against the incumbent when the economy is deteriorating. In a context of a severe economic crisis, we examine how fluctuations at the level of unemployment affect the vote for the party in government. We do so by using a survey experiment were we manipulate the level of unemployment.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;br&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;LAB EXPERIMENTS&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;em&gt;Political Attitudes and the Breakdown of Cooperation: Evidence from a Public-Good game&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This paper presents a public good game that can be used to introduce players to the conflict between social incentives to provide to the public good and constraints from individual incentives and political attitudes.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title></title>
      <link>/media/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>/media/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://www.huffingtonpost.com/2015/07/08/greece-polls-wrong_n_7754874.html?1436388088&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;Why The Polls In Greece Got It Wrong&lt;/a&gt;
Why the majority of the Greek polling companies failed to accurately predict the outcome of the elections?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://web.de/magazine/wirtschaft/griechenland-krise/griechenland-neuwahlen-stehen-parteien-loesung-30865430&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;Griechenland: Die Neuwahlen stehen bevor. Viele Parteien, doch keine Lösung?&lt;/a&gt;
An interview discussing Syriza’s coalition strategies, the refugee crisis and the extreme right in Greece.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://themonkeycage.org/2012/06/2012-greek-2nd-parliamentary-post-election-report/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;2012 Greek (2nd) Parliamentary Post-Election Report&lt;/a&gt;
A short report of the 2012 national election in Greece.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Economy and emotions, Makedonia,  (In print only)
An article on how sensational politics overtook reason during the economic crisis.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;SKAI News, 1st January 2017.
Discussing the implications of the Brain-Drain during the economic crisis in Greece.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://www.skai.gr/player/Radio/?mmid=279094&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;Skai Radio 100.3, Christina Vidou&lt;/a&gt;
Commenting on the problem of Brain-Drain in Greece&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;TV 100, “Polis, Politis, Politiki “, 12th June 2015
Panel discussion on the developments in Greek politics during the economic crisis (2009-) and the changes at the Greek party system after the victory of SYRIZA in 2015.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://makthes.gr/%CF%83%CF%85%CE%BD%CE%B5%CE%B4%CF%81%CE%B9%CE%BF-%CE%B5%CF%80%CE%B9%CF%83%CF%84%CF%81%CE%BF%CF%86%CE%AE-%CF%84%CE%BF%CF%85-%CE%B4%CE%B9%CE%BA%CE%BF%CE%BC%CE%BC%CE%B1%CF%84%CE%B9%CF%83%CE%BC%CE%BF/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;Macedonia, “Back to bipartisanship” by Vagellis Plakas, 06 October 2014&lt;/a&gt;
Discussing the implications of the economic crisis on party choice in Greece, who the crisis transformed the Greek party system and how left-right ideology lost ground while political issues such as the economy, the bailout agreements become more important determinants of party choice.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://makthes.gr/%CE%B1%CF%80%CF%8C-%CF%84%CE%BF%CE%BD-%CF%80%CE%BF%CE%BB%CE%B9%CF%84%CE%B9%CE%BA%CF%8C-%CF%83%CE%B5%CE%B9%CF%83%CE%BC%CF%8C-%CF%83%CF%84%CE%B7-%CF%81%CE%B5%CF%85%CF%83%CF%84%CF%8C%CF%84%CE%B7%CF%84/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;Macedonia, “From a political earthquake to political fragmentation” by Vagellis Plakas, 9 June 2013&lt;/a&gt;
Discussing the role of the economy on the results of the first elections during the economic crisis in Greece and on the new dimensions of economic voting such as the bailout-out agreements and the role of the EU in the economic reforms.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;THE ATHENS REVIEW OF BOOKS, Issue 30, June 2012.
From Laos to Golden Dawn: Reasons for supporting the radical right in the most recent elections. Vasiliki Georgiadou, Anastasia Kafe, Roula Nezi, Kostis Pieridis. (In print only)&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title></title>
      <link>/people/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>/people/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title></title>
      <link>/projects/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>/projects/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;(SELECTION OF PROJECTS I HAVE BEEN INVOLVED OR I AM CURRENTLY INVOLVED IN)&lt;/strong&gt;
&lt;br&gt;
&lt;br&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Preference Matcher&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;PreferenceMatcher is an academic consortium involving political scientists, social psychologists, computer scientists, and communication specialists from the University of Zurich, University of Twente, Cyprus University of Technology and Oxford Brookes University who collaborate in developing e-literacy tools designed to enhance voter education.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;“Change Through Crises? Solidarity and De-solidarization in Germany and Europe” (short: SoliKris)&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;European countries have experienced a set of severe crises over the past years. The research project Solikris (Change through Crisis? Solidarity and desolidarization in Germany and Europe) is based on two main assumptions: First, despite the lack of a causal connection between the various crises, there is a significant overlap and reinforcement of their effects and influence on the society, politics, and the behaviour of European states to each other. Second, all these crises have one thing in common. They have influenced the feeling of solidarity within the society as it presents itself among individuals, social groups and to an extreme form also European states. The drop of solidarity could lead to an extreme desolidarization. However, in some cases, the crises lead to increasing solidarity. This is a question that needs to be treated empirically. The central research question of Solikris is: What are positive and negative effects on solidarity within a society and between European countries that have brought the various crises since 2006? This question allows us to identify positive and negative influences and the conditions and circumstances under which they were made possible.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Funded by: Federal Ministry of Education and Research (BMBF)
Duration: 1.12.2017 – 30.11.2020
SoliKris is a collaborative research project bringing together more than a dozen social scientists from the GESIS Leibniz Institute for the Social Sciences, the University of Heidelberg, and the WZB Berlin Social Science Center.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Political Parties and Interest Groups in Southern Europe.  (2016 -)&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The project’s main goal is to analyze the relationship between parties and interest groups using a comparative and longitudinal approach. Third-wave Southern European democracies (Greece, Portugal, and Spain) will be used to address the following questions: How have political parties interacted with interest groups? What is the evolution of this linkage over time, in particular after the emergence of the recent economic crisis? Which factors can explain party-group interactions? How can we explain variation across different parties and countries? The empirical research is based on extensive data collection which includes not only the organizational dimension but also an examination of leadership profile, as well as new data collected through a questionnaire to interest groups and elite interviews. The final aim is to assess potential causes of party-group linkages, considering sociological, institutional and actors’ strategy as the main explanatory factors.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Designing &amp;amp; Operating an Infrastructure for the Empirical Inquiry of Political &amp;amp; Social Radicalism in Greece (2012-2015)
This project aimed to empirically record political and social radicalism in Greece during the economic crisis years.  Data have been collected by telephone interviews conducted in January 2015 prior to the 25 January 2015 Parliamentary Elections.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Access to data:
Political &amp;amp; Social Radicalism in Greece: First Round
Political &amp;amp; Social Radicalism in Greece: Second Round
Political &amp;amp; Social Radicalism in Greece: Third Round&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;INTUNE: Integrated and United? A Quest for Citizenship in an Ever Closer Europe (2006-09)
The IntUne project was a four-year project which officially started on the 1st September 2005 within the scope of the 6th Framework Programme and was coordinated by the University of Siena. The project aimed at studying the changes in the scope, nature, and characteristics of citizenship that result from the process of the deepening and enlargement of the European Union. During that time I was working as a research assistant for the Greek team, for the research area of the project concerning national elites.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title></title>
      <link>/teaching/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>/teaching/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;UNDERGRADUATE AND MASTER COURSES:&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;University of Surrey&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Research in Practice (POLM011) SS&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Research Methods (POL2028) SS&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Econometrics (POL2045) WS&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Companion Website for modules in quantitative methods: &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.roulanezistats.com&#34;&gt;www.roulanezistats.com&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Electoral Systems and Voting (POL2046) SS&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;br&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;University of Konstanz and Cologne Business School&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Empirical Social Research,  Cologne Business School, WS 2016
Radical right parties in Europe, University of Konstanz, WS 2014
Political representation in Western Europe, University of Konstanz, SS 2014&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;br&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;COURSES ON ADVANCED RESEARCH METHODS:&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;ECPR Course on Age-Period-Cohort models&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;22 February-1 March 2019, Bamberg, Germany&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This course is designed to give participants a deep knowledge of Age-Period-Cohort (APC) Models. Those are models that help social scientists to examine whether time-varying changes in social and political phenomena are due to the biological and social process of aging (age effects), social or economic factors, for example, an economic crisis (Period effects) or due to the unique experience of a group, for example children socialised under an authoritarian regime (cohort effects). What makes the analysis of those effects interesting and methodologically challenging is the so-called “identification problem”; The age-period-cohort conundrum refers to the problem of separating the effects of age, periods and cohorts. Upon completion of the course participants will have an understanding of the identification problem in the study of aging and cohort analysis and an understanding of the different methods developed to overcome the identification problem. Participants will also be familiar with the limitations of these methods and will also be able to know which method to use depending on their own research question.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;ECPR Course on Survey Design&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;2-9 March 2018, Bamberg, Germany&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This course introduced students to the theory and the practicalities of survey design. The course used the Total Survey Error scheme as the main theoretical framework and based on that discussed survey sampling, mode selection, question and questionnaire design, fieldwork implementation; non-response and data archiving.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Introduction to R&lt;/strong&gt;
5 days seminar
30 May 2016 to 3 June 2016
Centre for political research, Panteion University of Athens, Greece&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The course covered the following topics:
Terminology used in R such as objects, data frames, packages, functions. How to install packages. How to install and use R Studio. How to read, save and export data. Basic statistics. Graphs with R  (Basic graphs, ggplot2 and interaction terms). Regression analysis and diagnostics&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;TEACHING AT SUMMER SCHOOLS:&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Module III: Reforming the financial and monetary system
Alternative Economic and Monetary Systems 2017 (Vienna, July 26 – August 11, 2017, in English)
From theory to practice: Greece and Iceland.
The political and economic situation of Greece and Iceland. (Public event)&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
